Guide to the Joaquim Sancho Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Joaquim Sancho papers
1936-1945
MS 2080
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
.21
(1 box)
Papers of Joaquim Sancho, a Spanish Civil War soldier fighting for the Republican cause. The bulk of the collection comprises Sancho's correspondence, spanning from the period of his military service in the Regular Spanish Army, No. 55, VIII Grupo and the 4th Company, 103rd Mixed Brigade, through his time as a prisoner in a Nationalist concentration camp. Before Sancho's capture, he typically wrote in Catalan, and during his capture he wrote in Spanish. In addition to correspondence, the collection includes a 1938 manuscript map with notes of the trench works of the 103rd Mixed Brigade; lists of phone calls and correspondences Sancho sent and received; a likeness of Gandhi drawn on the back of Sancho's registration for the Republican Independent Party of Catalunya; a likeness of Franco drawn on an envelope; and manuscript and printed fragments of material pertaining to the war.
Sancho, Joaquim
Scope and Contents
Papers of Joaquim Sancho, a Spanish Civil War soldier fighting for the Republican cause. The bulk of the collection comprises Sancho's correspondence, spanning from the period of his military service in the Regular Spanish Army, No. 55, VIII Grupo and the 4th Company, 103rd Mixed Brigade, through his time as a prisoner in a Nationalist concentration camp. Before Sancho's capture, he typically wrote in Catalan, and during his capture he wrote in Spanish. In addition to correspondence, the collection includes a 1938 manuscript map with notes of the trench works of the 103rd Mixed Brigade; lists of phone calls and correspondences Sancho sent and received; a likeness of Gandhi drawn on the back of Sancho's registration for the Republican Independent Party of Catalunya; a likeness of Franco drawn on an envelope; and manuscript and printed fragments of material pertaining to the war.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the Librarian for the Latin American and Iberian Collections, 2017. Purchased by the Librarian for the Latin American and Iberian Collections from Kevin Jackson, History Revealed, 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The material is arranged by type of material and therein chronologically.
Biographical / Historical
Joaquim Sancho, Spanish Nationalist and soldier in the Spanish Civil War, served in the Regular Spanish Army, No. 55, VIII Grupo. In 1939, he was transferred to the 4th Company, 103rd Mixed Brigade. He had three other family members fighting for the Republicans, one in the 141st Mixed Brigade and another in the 109th Mixed Brigade, 3rd Battalion, Major of Transmissions. Following his rehabilitation, he served in the Spanish army in Morocco.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939; Sancho, Joaquim
- Correspondence, 1936- (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1937- (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1938- (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1939- (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1942- (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1943- (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Empty envelopes, 1936-1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Logs, 1938-1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Maps, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Sketches, 1936-1943 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Poems, 1936-1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous fragments, 1936-1943 (Box 1, Folder 13)